業界[ぎょうかい]:business world/business circles/(the) industry
（アキラ）業界のウワサによると
According to rumors from the industry,
ミゼット:midget, シリーズ:series, 発売禁止[はつばいきんし]:prohibition of sale
ミゼットシリーズが
発売禁止になったのは
the reason the Micet series was taken off the market
隠し撮り[かくしどり]:taking pictures secretly/peeping photo, 盗み聞き[ぬすみぎき]:eavesdropping/tapping, 悪用[あくよう]:abuse/misuse/perversion
隠し撮りや盗み聞きに
悪用できるからだそうです
was because it facilitated breaches of privacy such as covert photography and eavesdropping.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness
私はパン！　絶対にパン！
I want toast!
Definitely toast!
どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives)
（アキラ）僕は どっちでもいいよ
I really don't care—
ダメ！　あんたもパン
No! You must have toast, too!
日本人[にほんじん, にっぽんじん]:Japanese person/Japanese people, ご飯[ごはん]:cooked rice|meal, 納豆[なっとう]:natto (fermented soybeans)
（父）日本人は ご飯に納豆
Japanese eat natto on rice.
Natto is a traditional Japanese meal made from fermented soybeans, popular for breakfast.
納豆[なっとう]:natto (fermented soybeans), 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off
イヤ！　納豆 食べろって言うなら
これからパンしか食べないわよ
No way!
If you make me eat natto, I'll only eat toast from now on.
納豆[なっとう]:natto (fermented soybeans), 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
これで もう
納豆は食べさせられないわよね
That way, you'll never have me eating natto again!
納豆[なっとう]:natto (fermented soybeans), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
パンに納豆なんてありえないもの
You most definitely can't have natto with toast.
毎日[まいにち]:every day, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
僕 毎日 パンなんてヤダよ
I don't wanna eat toast every day!
なさる:to do
あんたもパンにしなさい
You must have toast!
屁理屈[へりくつ]:sophism/quibble/hair-splitting
（母）また屁理屈(へりくつ) 言って
There you go again with your bickering.
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
じゃあ フミエは夏休みの間
ずっとパン
All right, Fumie.
You'll only have toast during the summer break.
毎日[まいにち]:every day, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
えっ 毎日なんてヤダよ！
Eh?!
But I don't want it every day!
子供[こども]:child/children
子供じゃあるまいし
ワガママ言わないの
You're not a child anymore.
Stop being picky.
My Sister's a Bully Case 34
（母）フミエ！　アキラ！
Fumie.
Akira.
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||
夏休みだと思って
いつまでも寝てないの
Don't think you can sleep all day just because it's summer break.
毎日[まいにち]:every day, 飽きる[あきる]:to get tired of/to lose interest in/to have enough
（フミエ）
あ～ 毎日 パンじゃ飽きるわ
Ah...
You sure get sick of eating toast every day.
なさる:to do, とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
（母）ほーら 見なさい
ママの言ったとおりでしょ
You see?
Isn't it exactly like your mom told you?
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
なんかさ
もっといいもの食べさせようよ
You should let us eat something better.
可愛い[かわいい, かわゆい]:cute|dear|cute little, 子供[こども]:child/children
可愛い子供にはさ
After all, we're your beloved children.
（母）自分で言ったんでしょ
You're the one who wanted this, aren't you?
残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
残さず食べないと
大きくなれないわよ
If you don't eat everything, you won't grow any bigger.
はい あなた
Here you go, dear.
（父）ほら 見ろ
Look at this.
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, ご飯[ごはん]:cooked rice|meal
だから パパみたいに
ご飯にしておけばよかったんだ
You should've done as I said.
あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
アキラ これあげる
（アキラ）んっ？
Akira, I'm giving this to you.
残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
残さず食べないと
大きくなれないわよ
If you don't eat it to the very last crumb, you won't grow any bigger.
ごちそう:feast/treating (someone)|to treat (someone, e.g. to a meal)
ごちそうさま！
Thanks for the meal!
This is a Micet.
ミゼット:midget, 飼う[かう]:to keep (a pet or other animal)/to raise/to have, 小さな[ちいさな]:small/little/tiny, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 猫[ねこ, ネコ]:cat|shamisen|geisha||, 猫[ねこま]:cat
（アキラ）これはミゼット
僕が飼っている小さな電脳猫です
It's a small cybercat.
親指[おやゆび]:thumb, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 大きさ[おおきさ]:size/dimensions/volume, 特技[とくぎ]:special skill
親指くらいの大きさで
ちょっとした特技があります
It's as large as a thumb,
and it has a special function.
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, マトン:mutton
普通のペットマトンは―
A normal petmaton
映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind, 音声[おんせい, おんじょう]:voice/(the concept of) sound, 記録[きろく]:record|record (e.g. in sports)|to record|
見た映像や聞いた音声を
記録できません
can't record the things it sees or the voices it hears.
プライバシー:privacy, 著作権[ちょさくけん]:copyright, 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
プライバシーや
著作権上の理由だそうです
That's because of privacy and copyrights and stuff like that.
ミゼット:midget
でも このミゼットだけは―
But a patch that enables these things for Micet started to circulate,
回避[かいひ]:evasion/avoidance, パッチ:patch, 流出[りゅうしゅつ]:discharge/outward flow|leak of (private) information or pictures, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
それを回避できるパッチが
流出してしまい
録画[ろくが]:(video) recording, 録音[ろくおん]:(audio) recording
録画や録音ができます
so now it's possible to record both sound and video.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, パッチ:patch, 当てる[あてる]:to hit|to expose|to apply (e.g. patch)||
もちろん
僕もパッチを当てています
Of course, I installed the patch too.
見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered, 即座[そくざ]:immediate/right there on the spot/impromptu, 消去[しょうきょ]:elimination/erasure/dying out, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
だから サッチーに見つかったら
即座に消去されてしまいます
So if Satchii ever found out,
it would delete mine immediately.
賢い[かしこい]:wise/clever/smart, すばしっこい:nimble/smart/quick
でも こいつは賢いし
すばしっこいから
But this little guy is extremely fast and alert,
そんなヘマはしません
so it won't get caught easily.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 種類[しゅるい]:variety/kind|counter for different sorts of things, すでに:already/too late, 発売禁止[はつばいきんし]:prohibition of sale
もちろん この種類は
すでに発売禁止になっています
Of course, this type has already been taken off the market.
飼う[かう]:to keep (a pet or other animal)/to raise/to have, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, ラッキー:lucky
今も飼っている僕は
とてもラッキーです
As a matter of fact, I consider myself lucky to have one.
だって…
Because...
残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 食べる[たべる]:to eat|to live on (e.g. a salary)/to live off, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great
残さず食べないと
大きくなれないわよ
If you don't eat it to the very last crumb, you won't grow any bigger.
My Sister's a Bully Case 25
映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, いざというとき:when it's important/when it comes to the crunch/when push comes to shove
（アキラ）こういう映像を残せば
いざというとき―
Because with these records,
when it comes down to it,
やり込める[やりこめる]:to talk down/to corner someone in an argument
姉をやり込めることが
できるからです
I can make my sister shut up.
これが僕の姉 フミエです
This is my sister, Fumie.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 生態[せいたい]:mode of life/ecology|(animal) territory, 記録[きろく]:record|record (e.g. in sports)|to record|, 紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral
今日は姉とその友達の
生態の記録を紹介したいと思います
Today, I would like to show the real story of my sister and her friends.
申す[もうす]:to say/to be called|to do, 遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule
あっ 申し遅れました
Ah, I forgot to mention...
小学[しょうがく]:elementary school/primary school/grade school, 年生[ねんせい]:pupil in ... year/student in ... year
僕はアキラ 小学４年生です
I'm Akira.
I'm a fourth year elementary school student.
身長[しんちょう]:height (of body)/stature, 体重[たいじゅう]:body weight/one's weight
姉は身長１２０
体重27キロです
My sister is a hundred and twenty centimeters tall,
Chronicles of the
Living Creature
and she weighs twenty-seven kilograms.
年生[ねんせい]:pupil in ... year/student in ... year, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny
６年生にしては
小さいです
For a sixth grader, she's quite small.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 増える[ふえる]:to increase/to multiply
最近 増えたわよね キュウちゃん
There've been a lot more Kyuu-chans lately.
（ヤサコ）キュウちゃん？
"Kyuu-chans"?
球体[きゅうたい]:sphere/globe/orb
知らないの？
球体だからキュウちゃん
You've never heard of 'em?
They're "Kyuu-chans" because they're spherical.
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
で 仕事は何？
So what's the assignment?
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 壁[かべ, へき]:wall|barrier|Chinese "Wall" constellation (one of the 28 mansions)
（ヤサコ）あっ ペットが
壁の中に入っちゃったの
My pet has entered a wall.
穴[あな]:hole|deficit|vacancy||, 穴[けつ]:ass|rear|acupuncture point|, 消える[きえる]:to go out/to vanish/to disappear
穴があったんだけど
すぐに消えちゃったの
There was a hole there,
but it disappeared right after.
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly
ふーん…
あっ あの…
私 小此木(おこのぎ)優子(ゆうこ)っていうの
Um...
My name is Yuko Okonogi.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
よろしく…
Nice to me—
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient
ふむ… 空間が古いわね
This space is so obsolete.
料金[りょうきん]:fee/charge/fare
料金は200メタだけどいい？
The price is 200 meta, okay?
メタ？　メタって何？
Meta?
What're meta?
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 渡す[わたす]:to ferry across (e.g. a river)|to lay across|to hand over
あんた メタバグも知らないの？
ほら さっき渡した…
What? You don't even know what a metabug is?
Remember? It's like the one I gave you earlier.
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures
（フミエ）そう それ
それでちょうどです
Yeah, that one!
That one will do just fine.
非常[ひじょう]:emergency|extraordinary/unusual, がめつい:greedy/grasping/predatory, 性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition
（アキラ）
姉は 非常に がめつい性格です
My sister is extraordinarily cunning when it comes to money.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, ハッキング:hacking, 仕返し[しかえし]:being even with/reprisal/tit for tat
（フミエ）もちろん
ハッキングで仕返ししてやったわ
Needless to say, I got back at him by hacking.
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 枯渇[こかつ]:drying up/becoming exhausted/running dry
（アキラ）特にメタバグが
枯渇してからというもの
Especially since metabugs are becoming rare.
ミゼット:midget, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
僕やミゼットの見つけてきた
クズバグも―
She takes each and every metabug Micet or I collect.
巻き上げる[まきあげる]:to roll up|to take away|to blow up (dust)
すぐに巻き上げます
ミッション:mission, 主役[しゅやく]:leading part/leading actor/leading actress
そして こいつが…
このミッションの主役よ
And now this...
The key player for this mission.
Is this also from Megasia?
しもべ:servant/manservant/menial
（アキラ）これはオヤジ
姉のしもべです
This is Oyaji,
They don't sell this.
my sister's slave.
変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, マトン:mutton
オヤジは
ちょっと変わったペットマトンで
Oyaji is a kind of bizarre petmaton.
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 耐久性[たいきゅうせい]:durability, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all
古い空間での耐久性が
とても強いのです
Even in obsolete Space,
it's very resistant.
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
仕事だ オヤジ！
Time to work, Oyaji!
So next we slap a metatag on it.
メタタグ:META tag, 貼る[はる]:to stick|to stretch|to form (e.g. ice on a pond)||
あとはメタタグを貼って
もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, メタタグ:META tag
（アキラ）メガばあにもらった
メタタグだけでは―
She even sends it into obsolete Spaces,
And now it has increased protection.
長持ち[ながもち]:long-lasting/long-wearing|nagamochi, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 潜る[くぐる]:to go under|to dive (into or under the water)|to evade|, 潜る[もぐる, むぐる]:to dive (into or under water)|to get under|to hide oneself (esp. from the government)
長持ちしないような
古い空間まで潜って
where it wouldn't last long without Mega-baa's metatag.
Get in there right now, Oyaji!
取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
メタバグを取ってきます
And from there, it takes metabugs.
出所[しゅっしょ, でどころ]:origin|birthplace|release (discharge) from prison||, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 物質[ぶっしつ]:material/substance|matter
メタバグは出所不明の電脳物質で
Metabugs are a mysterious cybersubstance,
That's what a metabug is.
子供[こども]:child/children, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 通貨[つうか]:currency, 価値[かち]:value/worth/merit
子供の間でだけは
通貨の価値があります
and they only have value among kids.
It's a special product of Daikoku City.
I don't know why, but you can only get them here.
（アキラ）この人はヤサコさん
This girl is Yasako.
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 市[いち]:market/fair, 市[し]:city, 引っ越す[ひっこす, ひきこす]:to move (house)/to change residence, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
この間 大黒市(だいこくし)に引っ越してきた
すごくいい人です
She just moved to Daikoku City,
Fog!
and she's a wonderful person.
本名[ほんみょう, ほんめい]:real name, 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
本名は“優しい子”と書いて
優子なんだけど
Her name is written with the kanji for "gentle girl" and is read "Yuko,"
訓読み[くんよみ]:kun-yomi (Japanese reading of character), ニックネーム:nickname
それを訓読みして
ヤサコってニックネームです
so in its alternate Japanese reading, it makes her nickname "Yasa–ko."
あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), しゃべる:to talk/to chat/to chatter
あんまり
しゃべったことないけど―
I've never talked to her much,
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light), とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle, 感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression, お姉さん[おねえさん]:elder sister|(vocative) young lady|miss (referring to a waitress, etc.)||
名前のとおり
とても優しい感じのお姉さんです
but just like her name says, she's a very gentle girl.
You don't have any other scratches, do you?
I can't believe it's just a coincidence...
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
全然 関係ありませんが―
This has nothing to do with my story, but...
優しい[やさしい]:tender/kind/gentle, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 憧れる[あこがれる]:to long for/to yearn after/to admire, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
僕は優しい女の人って
すごく憧れてしまいます
I really like gentle girls.
遅れる[おくれる]:to be late/to be delayed/to fall behind schedule
ごめんね 遅れちゃって
I'm sorry for being late.
デンスケ！
Densuke!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
（ヤサコ）こ… 今度は何？
What is it now?
いよいよ:more and more/all the more|at last, お出まし[おでまし]:appearance/presence
いよいよ サッチーのお出ましだわ
In the end,
Satchii has come too!
（サッチー）
ボク サッチー ヨロシクネ
Me Satchii!
Nice to meet ya!
（アキラ）これはサッチー
This is Satchii.
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 市[いち]:market/fair, 市[し]:city, 最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 導入[どうにゅう]:introduction/bringing in/leading in, 強力[きょうりょく]:powerful/strong, 強力[ごうりき]:herculean strength/mountain carrier-guide, ウイルス:virus, 駆除[くじょ]:extermination (esp. pests)/expulsion/destruction, ソフト:soft
大黒市が 最近 導入した
強力なウイルス駆除ソフトです
It's a gigantic antivirus software
that Daikoku City installed recently.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
でも すごくバカなので―
But it's extremely stupid.
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, イタズラ:mischief/prank/trick, 道具[どうぐ]:tool/implement|means, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 子供[こども]:child/children
普通の電脳ペットや
イタズラ道具を持っている子供にも
It tries to "format ray" everything relentlessly,
容赦[ようしゃ]:pardon/forgiveness|leniency, フォーマット:(computer) format, 光線[こうせん]:beam/light ray, 撃つ[うつ]:to shoot (at)|to attack/to defeat
容赦なくフォーマット光線を
撃ってきます
such as normal cyberpets or kids' toys.
フォーマット:(computer) format, 光線[こうせん]:beam/light ray
あっ フォーマット光線というのは
Ah, "format ray" is just a name I invented randomly.
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily
僕が勝手につけた名前なのですが
光線[こうせん]:beam/light ray, 浴びる[あびる]:to dash over oneself (e.g. water)/to take (e.g. shower)|to suffer (e.g. an attack), ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, マトン:mutton, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
光線を浴びると
ペットマトンは死んでしまうし
That's the ray that kills a petmaton when it hits them.
Also, the glasses' user's information, which is stored on a server,
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, ユーザー:user, サーバー:server
メガネのユーザーは
メガネサーバーに入っている―
情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.), しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
ＯＳの情報を壊されてしまいます
is damaged.
自動[じどう]:automatic/self-motion|intransitive verb, 修復[しゅうふく, しゅふく]:restoration/repair/mending, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from)
ＯＳの自動修復が始まると―
If the auto-restore function of the OS starts,
お年玉[おとしだま]:New Year's gift (usu. money given to a child by relatives and visitors), ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 強制的[きょうせいてき]:forced/compulsory, 引き落とす[ひきおとす]:to pull down/to automatically debit (from a bank account)
お年玉２年分ぐらいが
強制的に引き落とされちゃいます
you're forcibly charged the equivalent of two years' otoshidama.
As a basic defense,
対抗[たいこう]:opposition/antagonism, 手段[しゅだん]:means/way/measure
姉は対抗手段として―
額[がく]:picture (framed)|amount or sum (of money), 額[ひたい]:forehead/brow, ビーム:beam, 発射[はっしゃ]:firing/shooting|ejaculation, ソフト:soft, インストール:installation (esp. software), してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
額からビームを発射するソフトを
インストールしています
my sister installed some software that enables her forehead to shoot a beam.
Because Satchii is simply executing the orders it receives,
もっとも:most/extremely, もっとも:but then/although|reasonable
もっとも サッチーは―
命ずる[めいずる]:to command/to appoint, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
命じられた仕事をしている
だけなので
it doesn't do anything that would make it hated.
罪[つみ]:crime|penalty|fault|
罪はありません
逆恨み[さかうらみ]:being resented in return|unjustified resentment through misunderstanding
姉の逆恨みです
My sister just hates it unfairly.
（サッチー）ボク サッチー
Moreover, Satchii is under the control of the Ministry of Posts,
ちなみ:association/link|pledge (esp. for marriage), 学校[がっこう]:school, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
（アキラ）
ちなみに郵政局のサッチーは
学校や神社に入れません
so it can't enter schools or Shinto shrines.
学校[がっこう]:school, 文部[もんぶ]:Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology, 局[きょく]:bureau|office (e.g. post, telephone)|affair|, 局[つぼね]:court lady|separate room in a palace (esp. for a lady) (Heian period)|room for a very low class prostitute|, 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine, 文化[ぶんか]:culture/civilization|Bunka era (1804.2.11-1818.4.22), 管轄[かんかつ]:jurisdiction/control
なぜなら 学校は文部局
神社は文化局の管轄だからです
That's because schools are under the Ministry of Education's jurisdiction,
縦割り[たてわり]:dividing vertically/vertical split/top-to-bottom sectioning, 行政[ぎょうせい]:administration, さまさま:our gracious (e.g. Queen)/honorific that attaches to name of a person or thing that has bestowed grace or favour upon you
縦割り行政さまさまです
and shrines are under the Ministry of Culture's jurisdiction.
We've learned so many things...
勉強になる[べんきょうになる]:to gain knowledge/to be illuminated|enlightening
勉強になるわ
って… 京子(きょうこ)！
Kyoko!
Poop!
（京子）ウンチ！　ヒヒヒヒッ
Run!
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
逃げて！
Stop!
（ハラケン）待て！
This is Haraken.
（アキラ）
この人はハラケンさんです
He seems to be quite absent-minded,
ボケッと:being stupefied/doing nothing, 感じ[かんじ]:feeling/sense/impression
ハラケンさんは
ボケッとした感じで
He's the Biology Club president, Haraken.
年生[ねんせい]:pupil in ... year/student in ... year, 頼りない[たよりない]:unreliable/undependable|helpless
４年生の僕から見ても
頼りない人です
and even I, a mere fourth grader,
the vice president of the club by the way.
can't think of him as being reliable.
Despite this,
驚く[おどろく]:to be surprised/to be astonished, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 飼う[かう]:to keep (a pet or other animal)/to raise/to have
それなのに
驚くべきペットを飼っていたのです
he was raising an amazing pet.
Yup,
墓場[はかば]:graveyard/cemetery, 狩りに行く[かりにいく]:to go hunting
そう あれは バス墓場に
メタバグ狩りに行ったときでした
it was back then, during the metabug hunt at the bus graveyard.
I don't have any walls or mega-be left!
壁[かべ, へき]:wall|barrier|Chinese "Wall" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
壁もメガビーも
残ってないわ
Stop!
（ハラケン）待て！
Haraken!
（フミエ）ハラケン！
Sit.
座る[すわる]:to sit|to assume (a position)|to hold steady
（ハラケン）お座り
Shake hands.
お手
C'mon, we'll escape while it's like this!
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
さあ 今のうちに逃げよう
It'll only obey me for a minute.
僕の言うことを聞くのは
１分だけなんだ
Who on earth...
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
あ… あなた 一体…
...are you?
何者[なにもの]:who/what kind of person
（フミエ）…何者なの？
Believe it or not,
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
（アキラ）あろうことか
サッチーはハラケンさんのペット
Satchii is Haraken's pet.
To be precise, it's Haraken's aunt's pet.
正確[せいかく]:accurate/punctual/exact, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET
正確には ハラケンさんの
オバちゃんのペットだったのです
But this isn't really important.
大した[たいした]:considerable/great/important, 事件[じけん]:event/affair/incident, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
でも これは
大した事件ではありません
Did you
駅[えき]:station
あんた ダイチに
駅ビルのことチクッたろ！
tell Daichi
about what happened
at the station?
Please forgive me, Sis!
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
（アキラ）許してよ お姉ちゃん！
Sis?!
お姉ちゃん[おねえちゃん]:familiar form of "older sister"|form of address for young adult female
お姉ちゃん？
Yeah, he's my little brother, Akira.
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, 愚弟[ぐてい]:younger brother|stupid younger brother
そう 我が愚弟 アキラよ
Yeah, he's my little brother, Akira.
一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 思い出[おもいで]:memories/recollections/reminiscence
（アキラ）
一生の中で 一番イヤな思い出です
This is the most embarrassing moment of my entire life.
I'll probably suffer trauma as a result.
トラウマ:trauma (usu. psychological)
トラウマになりそうです
In the future, I'll become a policeman or a lawyer,
将来[しょうらい]:future (usually near)/prospects, 検事[けんじ]:public prosecutor, 弁護士[べんごし]:lawyer/attorney
僕は将来 検事か弁護士になって
and then I'll sue her and prove that she's guilty!
訴える[うったえる]:to raise|to appeal to (reason, emotions, etc.)|to complain||, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 有罪[ゆうざい]:guilt/culpability
そして姉を訴えて
必ず有罪にしてやります
I'll save all these recordings,
映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
こういう映像を
全部 残しておいて
and I'll use them as undeniable evidence in court.
裁判[さいばん]:trial/judgement/judgment, 証拠[しょうこ]:evidence/proof, 効果的[こうかてき]:effective/successful
裁判の証拠として
効果的に使ってやるのです
I'm so glad I have a Micet.
ミゼット:midget
ミゼットがいて本当によかった
And that's why
（講師）えー というわけで…
video and audio recordings that are taken illegally and in a concealed manner
違法[いほう]:illegal/illegality/invalid, 盗撮[とうさつ]:sneak photography/non-consensual photography/peeping photos, 盗聴[とうちょう]:interception (email)/wiretap/bug, 音[おと, ね]:sound|note|fame|, 映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind
違法に盗撮 盗聴された音や映像は
can't be used as evidence in court.
裁判[さいばん]:trial/judgement/judgment, 証拠[しょうこ]:evidence/proof, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
裁判の証拠としては使えません
"...can't be used."
使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
“使えません”
Wh-What?!
な… なんだって！
I've been very depressed since this morning.
朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||, 鬱[うつ]:depression/low spirits
今日は朝から本当に鬱(うつ)です
裁判[さいばん]:trial/judgement/judgment, 証拠[しょうこ]:evidence/proof, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, ことにする:to make a distinction/to differ/to be different, ことにする:to decide to|to pretend that
裁判の証拠にするのはやめて
自由研究に使うことにしました
Okay, so I gave up on using them as evidence in a court case,
and instead decided to use them for my own research.
タイトル:title, いきもの:living thing/animal, 記録[きろく]:record|record (e.g. in sports)|to record|
タイトルは
「いきものの記録」です
The title is, "Chronicles of a Living Creature."
広い[ひろい]:spacious/vast/wide, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
姉も広い意味で生き物だからです
That's because, in general, my sister is a "living creature."
我[われ, わ]:I|oneself|you|, 我[わが]:my/our/one's own, ながら:while/during|while, タイトル:title
我ながら
いいタイトルだと思います
I know I shouldn't say so myself, but I think it's a perfect title.
悪事[あくじ]:evil deed/crime/wickedness, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related, ひと休み[ひとやすみ]:(short) rest/breather/break
（アキラ）
姉の悪事に関しては ひと休みして
Let's take a break from my sister's bullying for a bit,
周囲[しゅうい]:surroundings/environs|circumference, 人々[ひとびと, にんにん]:each person/people/men and women, 目を向ける[めをむける]:to shift one's attention to/to shift one's focus on
その周囲の人々に
目を向けたいと思います
and talk about the other people here.
京子！
Kyoko!
（オバちゃん）ハァー
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
この子たち あんたの知り合い？
Do you know these two?
妹[いもうと]:younger sister, 妹[いも]:darling (only of a woman)|one's sister|friend
あっ はい　妹です
Yes, she's my little sister.
辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc., 子供[こども]:child/children, 危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||, 気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
この辺は子供には危ないから
気をつけて
This area is very dangerous. Be careful.
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
前にも事故があったのよ
There's even been an accident before.
ああ… 知ってます
Yes... I know.
Um, thank you very much.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
あの… ありがとうございました
Yasako!
ヤサコ！
Kyoko!
あっ 京子ちゃん よかった
I'm so glad to see you!
Ah, it's the stalker!
ストーカー:stalker
あっ！　ストーカー
サッチー！
It's Satchii!
（オバちゃん）待て
Stop!
Shake hands.
お手
Sit.
座る[すわる]:to sit|to assume (a position)|to hold steady
お座り
Wh-Who are you?
（ヤサコ）あ… あなたは？
You've finally found her!
見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
（ハラケン）
見つかったんだ？　よかった
Thank goodness!
Ken!
ケンちゃん
A-Auntie!
あっ オバちゃん
A-Auntie?!
（２人）オ… オバちゃん？
飼い主[かいぬし]:shepherd/(pet) owner
（アキラ）この人は
サッチーの飼い主 オバちゃんです
She's Satchii's master,
also known as Auntie.
Her real name is Tamako Harakawa.
本名[ほんみょう, ほんめい]:real name, 玉子[たまご]:eggs|hen egg|(an expert) in the making|
本名は原川(はらかわ)玉子(たまこ)といいます
She's called "Auntie" because she's Haraken's aunt.
叔母[おば, はくぼ]:aunt, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
ハラケンさんの叔母さんだから
オバちゃんと呼ばれています
Anyway, she's the person who installed Satchii in Daikoku City.
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 市[いち]:market/fair, 市[し]:city, 導入[どうにゅう]:introduction/bringing in/leading in
この人が大黒市に
サッチーを導入させた―
張本人[ちょうほんにん]:ringleader/originator/perpetrator
張本人だそうです
Her strong personality surpasses even my sister's.
人格[じんかく]:personality/character/individuality, 上回る[うわまわる]:to exceed (esp. figures: profits, unemployment rate, etc.)/to surpass/to be more than
その人格は姉を上回るもので
In fact, even if Satchii wasn't here,
たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful
もしサッチーがいなかったとしても
she'd still be the one who spreads chaos all over town.
謎[なぞ]:riddle/puzzle|enigmatic, 混乱[こんらん]:disorder/chaos/confusion, 街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, もたらす:to bring/to take/to bring about
謎と混乱を僕らの街に
もたらしたことでしょう
Hey, ya jerk!
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
こら お前！
こんな所で何やっとる…
What the hell are ya doin'...
...here?
…んですか？
You're a lifesaver, Auntie.
助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped
オバちゃん 助かったよ
（２人）ハラケン！
Haraken?!
This has nothing to do with my story, but...
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
（アキラ）全然 関係ないのですが
I really, really like
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, 憧れる[あこがれる]:to long for/to yearn after/to admire, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
む… 胸の大きい女の人って
僕 すっごく憧れてしまいます
girls with big breasts.
Cut it out!
Auntie is like my sister as far as personality goes,
性格[せいかく]:character/personality/disposition, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related, 似る[にる]:to resemble/to look like|to be similar (in status, condition, etc.)
（アキラ）オバちゃんは
性格に関しては姉と似ていますが
but as for the breasts,
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related
む… 胸に関しては
she's nothing like my sister, who's in sixth grade and is as flat as a board!
年生[ねんせい]:pupil in ... year/student in ... year, ペッタンコ:crushed flat/flattened/squashed, 大違い[おおちがい]:great difference|major mistake
６年生にもなって
ペッタンコな姉とは大違いです
Set to "Hide?
Yes
No
I reckon that my sister's breasts
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life
姉は きっと一生あのままです
will stay the same forever.
Hidden
Dammit! Dammit!
（ナメッチ）この！　この！
These guys
所属[しょぞく]:attached to/belong to/member, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, クラブ:nightclub, クラブ:club/fraternity/sorority
（アキラ）この人たちが
僕の所属していたクラブ
were in the same club as me.
They're the Daikoku Hackers.
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, メンバー:member/participant/attendee
大黒黒客(ヘイクー)のメンバーです
Daichi,
ダイチさん
Gachagiri,
ガチャギリさん
Namecchi,
ナメッチさん
Denpa,
デンパ:electromagnetic wave/radio wave/reception
デンパさん
and me.
そして 僕
But they're not that important.
重要[じゅうよう]:important/momentous/essential, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
しかし 重要なのは
この人たちではありません
Rather, their enemy is.
戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.)
戦っている相手です
That's Isako.
（アキラ）この人がイサコさん
Just like Yasako,
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
ヤサコさんと同じ
ユウコという名前ですが
her name's Yuko,
but it's written with different kanji—
字[あざ]:section of village, 字[じ]:character (i.e. kanji)|hand-writing|the ... word (i.e. "the L word" - "love"), 勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
字が違って
“勇ましい子”と書きます
the ones for "courageous girl."
体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 表す[あらわす]:to represent|to reveal|to express|, 表す[ひょうす]:to express/to show
“名は体を表す”とは
よく言ったものです
She's a very courageous girl indeed.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring
すごく勇ましい人です
This has nothing to do with my story, but...
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
全然 関係ありませんが
I really like
勇ましい[いさましい]:brave/valiant|stirring, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 憧れる[あこがれる]:to long for/to yearn after/to admire, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
僕は勇ましい女の人って
すごく憧れてしまいます
brave girls.
Anyway,
ともかく:anyhow/anyway/somehow or other, 駄菓子[だがし]:cheap sweets, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 売る[うる]:to sell
それは ともかく
駄菓子屋で売っている―
this "war" game, which was played with weapons sold at a dagashi store,
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 兵器[へいき]:arms/weapons/ordnance, つぎ込む[つぎこむ]:to invest in/to sink money into/to put into, 戦争[せんそう]:war, ごっこ:playing at (something)/game of make-believe/something done together
電脳兵器をつぎ込んだ
この戦争ごっこは
ended in a landslide victory.
圧勝[あっしょう]:complete victory, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
イサコさんの圧勝に終わりました
水面[すいめん, みなも]:water's surface, 同時[どうじ]:simultaneous/concurrent/same time, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.)
（アキラ）
水面下では姉とイサコさんも
同時に戦っていたようですが
I heard later on
that behind the scenes, Isako was also waging war against my sister at the same time,
忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless, 気づく[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
忙しくて 僕は気づきませんでした
but I was too busy and didn't notice at all.
両方[りょうほう]:both/both sides/both parties, 勝つ[かつ]:to win/to gain victory
でも イサコさんは
その両方に勝ったのです
Isako won both battles.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
（アキラ）すごい人です
She's awesome.
伝聞[でんぶん]:hearsay/rumor/rumour, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information
そして 姉からの伝聞情報では
And then, according to my sister's "Cyberbulletin,"
駅[えき]:station, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 破壊[はかい]:destruction/disruption|(application) crash
このイサコさんが
駅ビルの空間を破壊して
Isako was the one responsible for breaking the Space
大量[たいりょう]:large quantity/massive (quantity)/mass (e.g. mass production, mass transit, mass destruction), 引き出す[ひきだす]:to pull out/to take out/to draw out, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
大量のメタバグを
引き出したという話です
and extracting loads of metabugs.
以外[いがい]:with the exception of/excepting, 真相[しんそう]:truth/real situation
姉とヤサコさん イサコさん以外は
真相を知りません
Apart from Yasako, Isako, and my sister,
no one knows the whole truth behind the story.
活躍[かつやく]:activity (esp. energetic)/great efforts|to flourish
でも そのあとの
イサコさんの活躍を見ると
But, after studying Isako's moves,
本当じゃないかなって思います
I've come to believe that it's all true.
ついに:finally/at last|in the end, 一騎打ち[いっきうち]:personal combat/one-to-one fight
だって ついにサッチーと
一騎打ちをして
Well...
In the end, she also had a fight with Satchii,
勝つ[かつ]:to win/to gain victory, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
イサコさんは勝ってしまったんだ！
and she actually won!
（サッチー）
ボク ボク… サ… サッチー
Me-Me... Me Sa-Sa... Satchii...
Recovery Impossible
黒[くろ]:black|black go stone|guilt, 客[きゃく, かく]:guest/visitor|customer, 客[まろうど, まろうと]:visitor from afar/guest, 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to take over/to capture|to hijack (a vehicle), 乗っ取る[のっとる]:to conform to/to be in accordance with/to follow (rule, tradition, example, etc.)
（アキラ）だから イサコさんが
そのあと黒客を乗っ取って
That's how Isako was able to prevail over the Hackers,
追い出す[おいだす]:to expel/to drive out
ダイチさんを
追い出しちゃったときも
and why I wasn't surprised
やっぱり:too/also|still
僕は “やっぱりな”って
思っちゃいました
when she kicked Daichi out.
腕[うで]:arm|skill/efforts, 腕[かいな]:arm (esp. upper arm)|counter used to measure the thickness of round objects, 単なる[たんなる]:mere/simple/sheer, 小学生[しょうがくせい]:elementary school student/primary school student/grade school student
（イサコ）
あなたより腕が上の
単なる小学生よ
I'm just an elementary school student,
who's just way more powerful than you.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（アキラ）ダイチさんには悪いけど
I feel sorry for Daichi,
でも イサコさんは
サッチーより強いし
but not only is Isako stronger than Satchii,
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
ちょっと怖い人だなって
思っていました
I also find her kinda scary.
Do you want me to teach you...
ミゼット:midget, 調べる[しらべる]:to examine/to investigate/to check up, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
それでミゼットに ちょっと
イサコさんを調べさせてみたんです
So, I had my Micet
do some research about Isako.
そしたら…
At this point...
おじさん
Uncle!
（おじ）よく来たね
Thank you for coming.
退院[たいいん]:leaving hospital/discharge from hospital
どう？　もう退院できるの？
How are you?
Can you leave the hospital yet?
かかる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
まだ かかりそうなんだ
I think I'll be here a little longer.
おじさん 聞いて
Listen, Uncle...
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister, 戻ってくる[もどってくる]:to come back
もうすぐ
お兄ちゃんが戻ってくるの
My brother will be back soon!
うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
そうかい そうかい うれしいね
I see, I see.
Glad to hear it.
冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story
冗談じゃないのよ
I'm not joking!
うん 分かってるよ
Yes, I know.
（イサコ）
それを知らせに来ただけだから
I just came here to tell you that.
Bye.
意外[いがい]:unexpected/surprising, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
（アキラ）ちょっと
意外なものを見てしまいましたが
By chance, I discovered an unexpected side to her personality,
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 子供[こども]:child/children
イサコさんも
普通の子供なのかなって
so I kinda got a reassuring feeling that Isako is a normal girl, after all.
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice
少し安心しました
やっぱり:too/also|still, たくらむ:to scheme/to plan/to play a trick
でも やっぱり
何かをたくらんでいそうです
However, I strongly believe that she's up to something.
ミゼット:midget, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 収集[しゅうしゅう]:gathering up/collection/accumulation
さて 今日もミゼットを
情報収集のために
Anyway,
today I sent my Micet out to gather some info.
路上[ろじょう]:(on the) road/(on the) way/(in the) street, 放る[ほうる, ほる]:to throw|to throw away|to neglect, 放る[ひる]:to expel (from the body)/to excrete/to defecate
路上に放っています
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 映像[えいぞう]:reflection|video|image in one's mind, 持ち帰る[もちかえる]:to bring back/to carry home/to take out (e.g. food), 楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
どんな映像を持ち帰るか楽しみです
I can't wait to see what video it'll bring back.
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, ミゼット:midget, シリーズ:series
言い忘れましたが
ミゼットシリーズには
I forgot to mention this,
but in the Micet series,
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 種類[しゅるい]:variety/kind|counter for different sorts of things, 出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy), じゃんけん:rock, paper, scissors game
同じ種類に出会うと
じゃんけんをするという―
there's a special feature installed so that when two of the same type meet, they play rock-paper-scissors.
仕込む[しこむ]:to train|to acquire (information)|to stock||
デモが仕込まれています
もっとも:most/extremely, もっとも:but then/although|reasonable, 発禁[はっきん]:sale prohibited|suppression (of a book), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 種類[しゅるい]:variety/kind|counter for different sorts of things, めった:thoughtless/reckless|seldom (with neg. verb), 出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy)
もっとも 発禁になってから
同じ種類には めったに出会わず
Especially now that they've been banned from the market,
it never meets another of the same type.
じゃんけん:rock, paper, scissors game, 機会[きかい]:chance/opportunity, ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically
じゃんけんの機会は
ほとんどないようです
So as far as I know, it doesn't get the chance to play R-P-S.
（ミゼット）ニャ～オ
ミゼット:midget, ご苦労[ごくろう]:trouble (I have put you through)
あっ ミゼット
今日もご苦労さん
Ah, Micet.
You've done a good job today, too.
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
どう？　何か見つけた？
So?
Did you find anything?
ミゼット:midget, 同型[どうけい]:isomorphism/same shape/same type
おや？
これはミゼットと同型かな？
Oh?
Could this be a Micet of the same type?
あれ？　あれ？
Eh?
Eh?!
Why did it stop in the middle?
途中[とちゅう]:on the way/en route|in the middle of, 撮れる[とれる]:to be photographed|to be able to photograph
なんで途中から
撮れてないんだろう？
初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
こんなこと初めてだ
This is the first time it's done that...
まあ いいや
Well, whatever.
姉貴[あねき]:elder sister, 生態[せいたい]:mode of life/ecology|(animal) territory, 日記[にっき]:diary/journal, 編集[へんしゅう]:editing/compilation/editorial (e.g. committee)
姉貴の生態日記の
編集でもしよっかな…
Let's play around and edit my sister's real life diary...
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be, っちゅう:meaning/called/said
（フミエ）
全部 聞こえてるっちゅうの
I'm listening to everything, you know.
姉をナメんなよ
Don't underestimate your sister.
Watch out!
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||
（猫目(ねこめ)）危ない！
赤信号[あかしんごう]:red light (traffic)
赤信号だぞ
（ハラケン）すみません
The light is red.
Sorry...
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
友達が そこにいた気がして…
I felt as if... my friend was standing over there.
（猫目）ケガがなくてよかった
You're lucky you didn't get hurt.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, メガネ:spectacles/glasses
君のそれ 電脳メガネかい？
Are you wearing
cyberglasses?
（ハラケン）
えっ？　ああ… はい
Y-Yes...
気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care, 特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 横断[おうだん]:crossing|traversing horizontally|cutting horizontally, 歩道[ほどう]:footpath/walkway/sidewalk
（猫目）気をつけたほうがいい
特に横断歩道は
You'd better be very careful.
Especially at the zebra crossing.
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 増える[ふえる]:to increase/to multiply
（猫目）最近 事故が増えてるんだ
The number of accidents has been increasing lately.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 子供[こども]:child/children
君と同じメガネの子供のね
The victims, you know, were kids like you.
それじゃ
Later.
あっ あの…
Hey...
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 調べる[しらべる]:to examine/to investigate/to check up
（猫目）すごいじゃないか
よくここまで調べたね
Wow, this is amazing.
You've done a great job with such extensive research.
小学生[しょうがくせい]:elementary school student/primary school student/grade school student
君 小学生なんだよね？
You're an elementary school student, aren't you?
自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, イリーガル:illegal, 大した[たいした]:considerable/great/important
自由研究でイリーガルを？
大したもんだ
And you chose the Illegals for your research?
That's a big deal.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
さっき 事故のこと
言ってましたよね？
A moment ago,
you talked about the accidents, right?
Yeah.
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
何か事故と関係のある方ですか？
Were you involved in an accident?
（猫目）ああ いや…
Ah, no.
街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents), 出来事[できごと, できこと]:incident/affair/happening, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 調べる[しらべる]:to examine/to investigate/to check up
この街で起きた出来事を
いろいろ調べているだけなんだ
I'm just doing research on all the strange things that are happening in this town.
個人的[こじんてき]:personal/individual/private
個人的にね
On my own.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 子供[こども]:child/children, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
（ハラケン）さっき言ってた
メガネの子供の事故
What do you think about the accident involving the childrens' glasses
どう思いますか？
that you mentioned before?
レポート:report/paper, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 有力[ゆうりょく]:influential/prominent|strong, 説[せつ]:theory|opinion|rumour
（猫目）
ああ 君のレポートにもあるけど
一番 有力な説は―
As you wrote in your report,
the most probable explanation is
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 誤動作[ごどうさ]:malfunction
電脳ナビが
誤動作したというものだね
that the cybernavi was somehow manipulated
作用[さよう]:action/operation/effect
なんらかの作用で
by an unknown operation.
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
その“なんらかの”っていうのは
もしかして…
This "unknown operation" you're talking about,
could it be...?
イリーガル:illegal
イリーガル？
...an Illegal.
はい
Yes.
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor
（猫目）
確かに電脳ナビの事故現場では
As it turns out,
a black shadow is often seen near where cybernavi accidents occur.
黒い[くろい]:black|dark|illicit, 影[かげ]:shadow|reflection|ominous sign||, 目撃[もくげき]:witnessing/observing/sighting
よく黒い影が目撃されているが
イリーガル:illegal, 自体[じたい]:itself|one's own body|originally, 正体[しょうたい]:true character/true form|consciousness, 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance
イリーガル自体が
正体不明の今
But since we actually ignore the real nature of Illegals,
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, 域[いき]:region/limits/stage
事故との関係も
都市伝説の域を出ない
as well as their relation with these accidents,
this doesn't venture beyond the boundaries of urban legend.
仮説[かせつ]:hypothesis/supposition/fictional
ただ これは僕の仮説なんだが…
This is just my hypothesis,
イリーガル:illegal, 自然[しぜん]:nature|natural|naturally, 発生[はっせい]:outbreak|generation (e.g. of power or heat)|ontogeny, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 生物[せいぶつ]:living things/creature|biology, 生物[なまもの]:raw food/perishables
もしイリーガルが
自然発生した電脳生物だとしたら
but if Illegals happened to be a cybersubstance that is self-generated,
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
こう考えられないだろうか？
wouldn't it be possible to interact with them?
住みか[すみか, じゅうか]:dwelling/house/residence, 追う[おう]:to chase|to follow (a set order, a trend, etc.)|to drive out||, 絶滅[ぜつめつ]:destruction/extinction, 危機[きき]:crisis/danger/risk, 瀕する[ひんする]:to be on the verge of/to be about to/to be on the point of, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
住みかを追われ 絶滅の危機に
瀕(ひん)している生き物だと
I think that by eliminating their only possible habitat, we're driving them to extinction.
ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 機器[きき]:device/equipment/machinery, 逃げ込む[にげこむ]:to take refuge in/to succeed in running away
あるものは
ペットや電脳機器の中に逃げ込み
It's true that some of them
escape into cyberpets or cyberdevices.
無害[むがい]:harmless, 化[か]:action of making something/-ification, 新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 共存[きょうぞん, きょうそん]:coexistence, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||, 図る[はかる]:to plan|to plot|to aim for|
あるものは無害化して
新しい空間と共存の道を図り
Others, perhaps, become harmless and try living among us in a new Space,
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
自分たちが
帰ることのできる場所―
just looking for a place that they can call home...
安住[あんじゅう]:living in peace/being content with one's present position, 地[ち]:earth|place|territory||, 地[つち, つし]:earth|the earth (historically, esp. as opposed to the heavens)|low-quality torinoko-gami (containing mud)|, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
安住の地を
探しているのかもしれない
a safe place to live in.
仮説[かせつ]:hypothesis/supposition/fictional, 正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper
だが もし
その仮説が正しいとしても
But even if this hypothesis turns out to be correct,
this wouldn't even be the surface of what's really happening.
起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen, ほんの:mere/only/just, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document), すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
それは 今 起こりつつあることの
ほんの一部にすぎない
街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
今 この街で起こっている何かのね
Something's happening in this town.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
どういう意味ですか？
What... do you mean?
仮説[かせつ]:hypothesis/supposition/fictional
（猫目）僕の仮説では
According to my hypothesis, I think
事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 単なる[たんなる]:mere/simple/sheer, 偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy)
事故そのものは
単なる偶然だったんじゃないか
that the accident was only coincidental.
真相[しんそう]:truth/real situation, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 隠す[かくす]:to hide/to conceal
真相は別な所に隠されているんじゃ
ないかと思うんだ
I believe that the truth is hidden somewhere else.
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, うすうす:thinly/slightly/vaguely, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
実は君も うすうす
分かり始めているんじゃないか？
And I'm sure that you're beginning to understand it somewhat, aren't you?
気に入る[きにいる]:to be pleased with/to suit
僕は君のことが気に入った
I like you.
忠告[ちゅうこく]:advice/warning
だから 君のために
１つ忠告をしておこう
That's why,
for your own good, I'll give you a warning.
From now on, if you further your research...
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 深入り[ふかいり]:getting deeply into/becoming deeply involved in
これ以上 深入りするな
ハッ… あなたは？
Who are you?
あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 深み[ふかみ]:depth/deep place
あまり深みに入ると
If you dig deeper,
you won't be able to come back when you want to anymore.
意思[いし]:intention/wish/purpose, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
自分の意思では
戻れなくなってしまう
Just like your friend.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
君の友達のように
Who...
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, 何者[なにもの]:who/what kind of person
あなたは 一体 何者なんです？
Who are you?
自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation
（猫目）自由研究はウソだろ
Calling it "independent research"
was just a lie, right?
何を… 何を言って…
What...
What are you talking—
（猫目）会いたいんだろ？
You want to meet her, right?
捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), イリーガル:illegal, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner
（猫目）君が捜しているのは
イリーガルではなく その方法
The one you're looking for is not an Illegal.
However, this method...
自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, フリをする:to pretend
自由研究のフリをして
Pretending to do it for research...
なんの… ことですか？
What are you saying?
For now, restrain yourself.
ほどほど:moderate, なさる:to do
だが ほどほどにしておきなさい
あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 深入り[ふかいり]:getting deeply into/becoming deeply involved in, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
あまり深入りすると
君も彼女と同じようなことになる
If you dig too deep,
you'll end up the same as your friend.
Just like Kanna Hashihara.
葦原[あしはら, あしわら]:reed bed
葦原(あしはら)カンナのように…
How... do you know about Kanna?
なぜ カンナのことを…
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech
君は電脳コイルという
言葉を知っているか？
Have you heard of the words "Dennou Coil"?
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
電脳コイル？
Dennou...
Coil?
If you haven't,
出来事[できごと, できこと]:incident/affair/happening, 調べる[しらべる]:to examine/to investigate/to check up
（猫目）知らないなら
４年前の出来事を調べてみるといい
then you'd better investigate what happened four years ago.
Who...
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, 何者[なにもの]:who/what kind of person
あなたは
一体 何者なんだ？
Who are you?
I'm the one who's here to ensure the safety of you kids.
安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
君たちの安全を守る者だ
You'd better not take my warning lightly.
忠告[ちゅうこく]:advice/warning, 軽んずる[かろんずる]:to despise/to belittle/to look down on
僕の忠告を軽んじないほうがいい
Just a little bit...
会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association
（イサコ）
もうすぐよ もうすぐ会えるわ
Just a little longer and we can meet...
Brother...
お兄ちゃん[おにいちゃん]:familiar form of "older brother"|form of address for young adult male/mister
お兄ちゃん
Preview
Next time
on Dennou Coil:
The Boys from the Other Side of the Station.
The Boys from the
Other Side of the Station
See you next time!
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
駅[えき]:station, 向こう[むこう]:opposite side|over there|the other party|, 少年[しょうねん]:boy/juvenile/young boy
〝駅向こうの少年 〞
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに